<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>surus' blog</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/</link><description>Recent content on surus' blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 16:28:02 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.schlieper.ch/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rusty Trader</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/12/rusty-trader/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 16:28:02 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/12/rusty-trader/</guid><description>The source code for this project can be found here.
Motivation Almost a year ago, Fireship, a great Youtube creator and developer, released a video on his channel, where he created a stock trading bot based on the inverse Jim Cramer strategy. The idea behind this being, that Jim Cramer gives terrible stock picks and doing the opposite might actually result in a positive return. I was very intrigued by this video and decided to try it out myself.</description></item><item><title>voucherio --- Viscon Hackathon 2022</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/12/voucherio-viscon-hackathon-2022/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 16:28:11 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/12/voucherio-viscon-hackathon-2022/</guid><description>Our student association recently hosted a hackathon with the goal of creating a voucher marketplace for businesses (henceforth referred to as suppliers). The idea was to provide a platform for businesses to offer discounts and promotions to groups (henceforth referred to as seekers) and to thus simplify the purchasing of such amenities. The hackathon was a great success, with a diverse group of students coming together to work on the project.</description></item><item><title>STARTHack</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/08/starthack/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2022 15:33:37 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2022/08/starthack/</guid><description>New year new hack. After the success of the last hackathon, we decided to attend another one. This time we decided to go for a more ambitious project. For this hackathon we, a friend group of about 15 people, travelled from Zurich to St. Gallen to attend STARTHack, hosted by the university of St. Gallen.
The hackathon This hackathon was designed to be a 36 hour hackathon. The hackathon started on Friday at 10pm and ended on Sunday at 10am.</description></item><item><title>Viscon Hackathon 2021</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/10/viscon-hackathon-2021/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 15:33:29 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/10/viscon-hackathon-2021/</guid><description>After having finished a year of ETH I believed myself to be able to muster any problem thrown my way. After hearing from our student association, vis, that they were hosting a Hackathon at their VIScon, we signed up immediately. This was all of our first time participating in any kind of such competition and much like with this post, we didn&amp;rsquo;t really know what we were doing. I gathered four of my friends, some of whom were better programmers, and we dove in head-first.</description></item><item><title>Fun with integrations</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/06/fun-with-integrations/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 09:47:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/06/fun-with-integrations/</guid><description>In the first post of this series centered around my university degree I will be talking about integration. Now this topic wasn&amp;rsquo;t mentioned in our script but I rather stumbled upon it on youtube.
The premise is the following:
We assume that we have a function f(x) which we can integrate over the interval a to b.
Calculate the following integral: $$\int_{2}^{4}\frac{\sqrt{x}}{\sqrt{6-x} + \sqrt{x}} dx$$ Doesn&amp;rsquo;t look trivial now, does it?</description></item><item><title>Exam period</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/05/exam-period/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 15:37:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/05/exam-period/</guid><description>Since I am a student at ETH I will be entering my so called &amp;ldquo;holidays&amp;rdquo; in a week. They are &amp;ldquo;holidays&amp;rdquo; since they serve as 2 months of preparation for a series of exams. During this time I will be posting the one or the other concept, algorithm or thought experiment that fall into one of four subject:
Algorithms and Probabilities Algorithms and Probabilities, or AnW for short, is all about probabilistic algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Welcome</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/04/welcome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 19:50:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/04/welcome/</guid><description>Welcome to my blog. This is my first ever post and I&amp;rsquo;ll be going over what you can expect on here and how to navigate the site.
Introduction This will be a personal work where I outline interesting projects, small guides and other little quirks. The content will be mainly based around CS-related subjects as well as some interesting mathematical concepts.
Navigating this blog As any other blog this one has three components: The home page, where you will get a rough overview of the blog, the about page, where you get to find out more about this blog as well as about me and last but not least the Posts page where all of my posts will be listed.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/about/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/about/</guid><description>Welcome to my small blog. I will be posting interesting side projects, Hackathons I am participating in as well as interesting bits of knowledge I found during my lectures. About me I am a CS student currently in his third semester. I live in switzerland and am currently attending ETH. I am an avid coder and enjoy doing sports in my freetime, such as climbing and going to the gym.</description></item></channel></rss>