<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on surus' blog</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on surus' blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>&lt;a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a></copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 19:50:31 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Welcome</title><link>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/04/welcome/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 19:50:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://www.schlieper.ch/posts/2021/04/welcome/</guid><description>Welcome to my blog. This is my first ever post and I&amp;rsquo;ll be going over what you can expect on here and how to navigate the site.
Introduction This will be a personal work where I outline interesting projects, small guides and other little quirks. The content will be mainly based around CS-related subjects as well as some interesting mathematical projects.
Navigating this blog As any other blog this one has three components: The home page, where you will get a rough overview of the blog as well as the first polyring, the about page, where you get to find out more about this blog as well as about me.</description><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog. This is my first ever post and I&rsquo;ll be going over what you can expect on here and how to navigate the site.</p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>This will be a personal work where I outline interesting projects, small guides and other little quirks. The content will be mainly based around CS-related subjects as well as some interesting mathematical projects.</p>
<h2 id="navigating-this-blog">Navigating this blog</h2>
<p>As any other blog this one has three components: The home page, where you will get a rough overview of the blog as well as the first polyring, the about page, where you get to find out more about this blog as well as about me. And last but not least the <code>Posts</code> page where all of my posts will be listed.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-this-polyring">What is this &lsquo;Polyring&rsquo;?</h2>
<p>Polyring is a webring made by ![JulianXY][https://xyquadrat.ch/]. This webring links to likeminded CS students that are currently studying at ETH too. By clicking <code>next</code> you get to the next blog in the ring, where you&rsquo;ll find yet another polyring. This is a great way to discover new high-quality blogs.</p>
<p>To finish this up, I hope that you, however decides to visit this, have a good time and if noticed something unsettling or want to contact me, you&rsquo;ll find my details on the homepage. Thanks for dropping by :)</p>
]]></content></item></channel></rss>